Shusen Wang

Assistant Professor, Department of Computer Science, Stevens Institute of Technology

Phone: (551)263-6585 Email: swang134@stevens.edu Homepage: wangshusen.github.io

Research

Keywords Machine learning (ML), randomized linear algebra, optimization, big data, distrib-

uted computing.

Summary I am most interested in statistical ML and computational methods for ML. The goal

of my research is making large-scale ML more accurate and efficient. My thesis work is randomized algorithms for speeding up ML and matrix computation with loss of a limited amount of accuracy. My postdoctoral work at Berkeley is mainly the design of parallel ML and data analysis algorithms and the implementation using Apache Spark. I am also working on statistical ML theories and application

of ML.

Work Experience

from 2018 Tenure-track assistant professor; Department of Computer Science, Stevens

Institute of Technology (Hoboken, NJ, USA)

2016-2018 Postdoctoral Scholar; Department of Statistics, UC Berkeley, (Berkeley, CA, USA)

Advisor: Michael W. Mahoney

Research: randomized linear algebra and implementation

2014-2015 Research Intern; Baidu Big Data Lab (Beijing, China)

Mentor: Tong Zhang

Research: optimization algorithms

2012 Research Intern; Google Research (Beijing, China)

Research: randomized algorithms

2011-2012 Intern; Microsoft Research Asia (Beijing, China)

Mentors: Haixun Wang and Yangqiu Song

Project: probabilistic knowledge base

Education

2011-2016 Doctor of Engineering; Zhejiang University (Hangzhou, China)

Major: Computer Science

Advisor: Zhihua Zhang

Thesis: Large-Scale Machine Learning: A Randomized Approach and Theoretical

Analysis

2007-2011 **Bachelor of Engineering**; Zhejiang University (Hangzhou, China)

Major: Computer Science

Academic Service

Journal Reviewer

- Journal of Machine Learning Research 2015 to 2018
- SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing, 2017
- ACM Transactions on Mathematical Software, 2017
- Journal of Econometrics, 2017
- SIAM Journal on Matrix Analysis and Applications, 2017
- International Journal of Data Science and Analytics, 2018

Conference Committee Member or Reviewer

- NIPS 2014, 2015, 2017, 2018
- ICML 2017, 2018
- IJCAI 2015, 2017, 2018
- AAAI 2017, 2018

Major Honors & Awards

2014	Baidu Scholarship, awarded to 8 Chinese students in the world, US\$30,000
2013	Microsoft Research Asia Fellow, awarded to 10 students in Asia Pacific, US\$10,000
2012	Scholarship Award for Excellent Doctoral Student Granted by Ministry of Education, US\$5,000
2012-2014	National Scholarship for Graduate Students, 3 times, each time US\$5,000
	Journal Papers

- Scalable Kernel K-Means Clustering with Nystrom Approximation: Relative-Error Bounds. Shusen Wang, Alex Gittens, and Michael W. Mahoney. Accepted by Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR), conditioned on minor revisions; available at arXiv:1706.02803, 2017.
- Sketched Ridge Regression: Optimization Perspective, Statistical Perspective, and Model Averaging. Shusen Wang, Alex Gittens, and Michael W. Mahoney. Journal of Machine Learning Research (**JMLR**), 18:1-50, 2018.
- Efficient Data-Driven Geologic Feature Characterization from Pre-stack Seismic Measurements using Randomized Machine-Learning Algorithm. Youzuo Lin, Shusen Wang, Jayaraman Thiagarajan, George Guthrie, and David Coblentz. Geophysical Journal International, ggy385, 2018.
- Alchemist: An Apache Spark <=> MPI Interface. Alex Gittens, Kai Rothauge, Michael W. Mahoney, Shusen Wang, Lisa Gerhardt, Prabhat, Jey Kottalam, Michael Ringenburg, and Kristyn Maschhoff. Concurrency and Computation Practice and Experience (CCPE), Special Issue on the Cray User Group, 2018.

- Towards More Efficient SPSD Matrix Approximation and CUR Matrix Decomposition. Shusen Wang, Zhihua Zhang, and Tong Zhang. *Journal of Machine Learning Research* (JMLR), 17(210):1-49, 2016.
- SPSD Matrix Approximation vis Column Selection: Theories, Algorithms, and Extensions. Shusen Wang, Luo Luo, and Zhihua Zhang. *Journal of Machine Learning Research* (JMLR), 17(49):1-49, 2016.
- Improving CUR Matrix Decomposition and the Nystrom Approximation via Adaptive Sampling. Shusen Wang and Zhihua Zhang. *Journal of Machine Learning Research* (JMLR), 14: 2729-2769, 2013.
- EP-GIG Priors and Applications in Bayesian Sparse Learning. Zhihua Zhang, Shusen Wang, Dehua Liu, and Michael I. Jordan. *Journal of Machine Learning Research* (JMLR), 13: 2031-2061, 2012.

Preprints

- A Bootstrap Method for Error Estimation in Randomized Matrix Multiplication. Miles E. Lopes, Shusen Wang, Michael W. Mahoney. Under the review of *Journal of Machine Learning Research*; available at *arXiv:1708.01945*, 2017.
- Improved Analyses of the Randomized Power Method and Block Lanczos Method. Shusen Wang, Zhihua Zhang, and Tong Zhang. arXiv:1508.06429, 2015.

Conference Papers

- GIANT: Globally Improved Approximate Newton Method for Distributed Optimization. Shusen Wang, Farbod Roosta-Khorasani, Peng Xu, and Michael W. Mahoney. Accepted by Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS), 2018. Preprint available at arXiv:1709.03528.
- Error Estimation for Randomized Least-Squares Algorithms via the Bootstrap. Miles E. Lopes, Shusen Wang, and Michael W. Mahoney. In *International Conference on Machine Learning* (ICML), 2018.
- Accelerating Large-Scale Data Analysis by Offloading to High-Performance Computing Libraries using Alchemist. Alex Gittens, Kai Rothauge, Shusen Wang, Michael W. Mahoney, Lisa Gerhardt, Prabhat, Jey Kottalam, Michael Ringenburg, and Kristyn Maschhoff. In ACM SIGKDD Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (KDD), 2018.
- Sketched Ridge Regression: Optimization Perspective, Statistical Perspective, and Model Averaging. Shusen Wang, Alex Gittens, and Michael W. Mahoney. In *International Conference* on Machine Learning (ICML), 2017.
- Towards Real-Time Geologic Feature Detection from Seismic Measurements using a Randomized Machine-Learning Algorithm. Youzuo Lin, Shusen Wang, Jayaraman Thiagarajan, George Guthrie, and David Coblentz. In Proceeding of Society of Exploration Geophysics (SEG), 2017.
- Open Domain Short Text Conceptualization: A Generative + Descriptive Modeling Approach.
 Yangqiu Song, Shusen Wang, and Haixun Wang. In International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI), 2015.
- Improving the Modified Nystrom Method Using Spectral Shifting. Shusen Wang, Chao Zhang, Hui Qian, and Zhihua Zhang. In the 20th ACM SIGKDD Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (KDD), 2014.

- Efficient Algorithms and Error Analysis for the Modified Nystrom Method. Shusen Wang and Zhihua Zhang. In *Proceedings of the 17th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics, JMLR W&CP* (AISTATS), 2014.
- Making Fisher Discriminant Analysis Scalable. Bojun Tu, Zhihua Zhang, Shusen Wang, and Hui Qian. In the International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2014.
- Exact Subspace Clustering in Linear Time. Shusen Wang, Bojun Tu, Congfu Xu, and Zhihua Zhang. In the 28th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2014.
- Using The Matrix Ridge Approximation to Speedup Determinantal Point Processes Sampling Algorithms. Shusen Wang, Chao Zhang, Hui Qian, and Zhihua Zhang. In the 28th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2014.
- Transfer Understanding from Head Queries to Tail Queries. Yangqiu Song, Haixun Wang, Weizhu Chen, and Shusen Wang. In the 23rd ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM), 2014.
- Nonconvex Relaxation Approaches to Robust Matrix Recovery. Shusen Wang, Dehua Liu, and Zhihua Zhang. In International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI), 2013.
- A Scalable CUR Matrix Decomposition Algorithm: Lower Time Complexity and Tighter Bound. Shusen Wang and Zhihua Zhang. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS), 2012.
- Colorization by Matrix Completion. Shusen Wang and Zhihua Zhang. In the 26th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2012.
- Efficient Subspace Segmentation via Quadratic Programming. Shusen Wang, Xiaotong Yuan, Tiansheng Yao, Shuicheng Yan, and Jialie Shen. In the 25th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2011.